<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compleat history of the pretended Prince of Wales from his supposed conception by the late abdicated Qeen [sic], to the fatal exit of his true mother Mrs. Mary Grey. Wherein all the depositions of the witnesses procur'd by King James, are fairly stated and examined, and all that has been writ upon that subject consulted, in order to set the whole intrigue in its true light.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219471</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830939</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830939</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35401</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34166)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35401)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2048:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compleat history of the pretended Prince of Wales from his supposed conception by the late abdicated Qeen [sic], to the fatal exit of his true mother Mrs. Mary Grey. Wherein all the depositions of the witnesses procur'd by King James, are fairly stated and examined, and all that has been writ upon that subject consulted, in order to set the whole intrigue in its true light.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year. 1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Gathered in 4's.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Price 6d.</note>
                  <note>With a final page of advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James, --  Prince of Wales, 1688-1766 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Grey, Mary --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35401:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Compleat HISTORY Of the Pretended PRINCE OF WALES, FROM His ſuppoſed Conception by the Late Abdicated Qeen, to the Fatal Exit of his True Mother Mrs. <hi>MARY GREY.</hi> WHEREIN All the Depoſitions of the Witneſſes procur'd by King <hi>James,</hi> are fairly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and examined, and all that has been writ upon that Subiect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, in order to ſet the whole In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue in its true Light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year. 1696.</p>
            <p>Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:35401:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35401:2"/>
            <head>A Compleat HISTORY Of the Pretended PRINCE OF WALES, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>BEfore we come to relate the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of this Impoſture, it will not be amiſs to take notice of the State of affairs at the time when it was ſet on foot, which we find to have been thus. The late K. thought himſelf eſtabliſhed on the Throne by his ſucceſs againſt the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſtanding Army on Foot; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35401:3"/> in good Terms with the Pope and the <hi>French</hi> King, the Juncture ſeemed as proper as heart could wiſh to fall upon Methods for ſecuring the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks againſt all future Enquiries into former Miſdemeanors, and to Introduce their Religion to be that of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They knew the King to be gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing old and infirm, and Experience had taught them by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, that a Proteſtant Succeſſor could eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy the Romiſh <hi>Babel,</hi> which a Popiſh Predeceſſor had Rebuilt, and therefore the only way to prevent ſuch an after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clap was to entail the Crown on a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Heir; theſe were the true Cauſes that gave Birth to this horrid Impoſture, which being once reſolved on was mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thus.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Caſtlomain</hi> was ſent on a ſplendid Embaſſy to <hi>Rome,</hi> where tho' ſome might put Satyrical Taunts upon him by placing horns on the Gates at his publick Entrance, yet he brought matters to a good underſtanding betwixt the King and the Pope, in Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony whereof Count <hi>D' Ada</hi> was ſent bither as Nuncio, during whoſe ſtay at
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35401:3"/> 
               <hi>Whitehall</hi> the matter was concerted, and as neceſſary <hi>praludiums</hi> to ſuch a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Cheat, the Queens Mother muſt make preſents to the Lady of <hi>Lorretto,</hi> the King undertook a pilgrimage to St. <hi>Winefred's</hi> Well; and the Queen to further her Conception makes a Journey to the Bath.</p>
            <p>Such infallible means were enough to poſſeſs the Papiſts with an Invincible Faith, that they muſt needs attain their end, and therefore they gave it out with mighty aſſurance that the Queen would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have a Boy, and Mrs. <hi>Celier</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, who was very well known to be an Incomparable Widwife, for uſhering Popiſh ſhams into the world, in her printed Anſwer to the Queries of a certain Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pbraided him and ſome others for Laughing at her becauſe ſhe ſaid her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was full of Children; but it now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo true that ſhe hop'd we ſhould have a Prince of Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then juſt about the time of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Conception, Father <hi>Peters</hi> was made a Privy Councellor, to prevent its being conteſted by any of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Honourable board; and to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35401:4"/> ſtir them up to make Orders concerning the Queen and the Child, that ſo it might be ſpread thro' the Nation on the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the Privy Council. And the K. himſelf being Conſcious of his own and the Queens Imperfections, yet being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to carry on the Impoſture, was pleaſed to ſay <hi>that her pregnancy was a very odd thing,</hi> Inſinuating as if Heaven had wrought a Miracle in favour of his Religion.</p>
            <p>And to River the belief of her preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy in the minds of the people, he takes a Journey to <hi>Chattam,</hi> and in the mean time a feigned report of the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi>'s death was ounningly conveyed to his Siſter the Queen, who pretended a danger of Miſcarriage by the fright, and on this occaſion the King was ſent for back in all haſte.</p>
            <p>Then about 22 Weeks after the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Conception, it's given out that her Majeſty had Milk in her Breaſts, but tho ſeveral Proteſtants deſired it, they could never be permitted to View them, nay nor the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark,</hi> who was at that time going to the <hi>Bath;</hi> and whoſe Teſtimony of its truth if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35401:4"/> had been really ſo, would have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied all thoſe who entertained any doubt concerning it; certainly had the thing been real it was ſo much the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Court to have had the Princeſſes atteſtation of that affair, that they would without all doubt have ſolicited her to ſee and Witneſs it; eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they knew that a fallacy was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
            <p>The ſame circumſtances of an Impoſture are to be offered concerning her belly, which was never ſhown to, nor ſuffered to be felt by any Proteſtant Lady, and it was particularly obſerved by thoſe who did make it their buſineſs that the Circumference thereof was not large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for a Child ſo luſty; nor was it natural like other Womens, ſhe did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bend in the back, nor had ſhe the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion and Protention of the Hips that is uſual in Women with Child, and that was particularly taken Notice of on this occaſion in another Lady ſtanding by her.</p>
            <p>Another Evidence of the Impoſture was, the Parties immediately imployed about her, ſuch as <hi>Mrs. Wilks, Delabadie Turini, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:35401:5"/> a buſie rigid bigotted Villanous people, who had cunning enough to manage ſuch a Wickedneſs, and a Conſcience well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough prepared to digeſt it.</p>
            <p>In was obſerved in the next place that no other Nurſe was provided to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her but this <hi>Mrs. Delabadie,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as every Perſon of Quality, nay, moſt rich Citizens Wives, uſe to be better prepared; neither was there any Wet Nurſe, nor men Midwives beſpoke, tho ſhe uſed to be well provided in all thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects at her other Deliveries.</p>
            <p>Nay, her Doctors of Phyſick were not ſo much as ordered to attend againſt the 2d. Reclioning, and tho their Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Drs. have Chambers appointed about their Lodgings, at all their Courts and at all times, whether there be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion or none, and do attend at ſuch Chambers, yet her Doctors attended not, tho' the occaſion was ſo great, ſo that of four or five, there was but one ſo near as to be there till after the pretended de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delivery, the reaſon of which is plain, leſt they ſhould have been ſo deligent as to follow the Court, and by being too near about her diſcover the Cheat.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35401:5"/>
            <p>Another mighty evidence of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture was this, that the Queen for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting all octjcteions ought to have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven notice of the Houſe and Room where ſhe intended to lie in, that the Princeſſes, or any for them, might have ſearcht ſuch Room to ſee whether there was no falſe door, traps or other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences for Juggling; or if there were to nail 'em up, and to have ſuffered no more but one door, and to have likewiſe Guards kept at that door for ſome days before the delivery, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the direction of the Civil Law in ſuch Caſes: and which if the pregnancy had been real the King and Queen would certainly have not only agreed to but ſolicited that it might have been done, when they knew that a Cheat was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; but inſtead of this, it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times given out that ſhe intended to lie in at <hi>Windſor,</hi> at other times at <hi>Richmond,</hi> ſometimes at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, and anon at <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> again.</p>
            <p>The Law before mentioned doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo provide that the preſent Heir ſhall not only have Liberty to ſearch ſuch Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens belly before hand (which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35401:6"/> denied in this Caſe) but likewiſe tho they be ſatisfied of the pregnancy to make uſe of after Circumſpection leſt a dead Child ſhould be changed for a living one, or a Girl changed for a Boy. And for the better prevention of an Impoſture, this Law doth moreover direct that the Heir, or thoſe deputed by them might keep the pregnant Woman from going out of their ſight ſo many days before the pretended delivery; and unleſs ſuch directions be followed, it preſumes that an Heir is not truly born, how much more then in this Caſe when they were wilfully omitted and refuſed?</p>
            <p>For inſtead of due notice beforehand as Law and reaſon does require, the Bed was ſet up at St. <hi>James</hi>'s but one day before the pretended delivery, and the Queen was not at the place above 12 hours before the time, having neither Linen Nurſe nor Midwife about her; and that alſo in the night time when peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were aſleep and could not know of her going thither, ſo that there was no time allowed to make due Obſervation of paſſages as the above mentioned Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in ſuch caſes.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:35401:6"/>
            <p>We ſhall next Conſider the place, to which one would think ſhe ſhould have had the greateſt A verſion imaginable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all her other Children born there died; but however Inconvenient it might be upon that account it was the moſt Convenient place in the World for an Impoſture, by reaſon of the ſituation of the adjoining Convent, and at the ſame time the Park Gates were kept Lockt for their farther ſecurity.</p>
            <p>It muſt alſo be obſerved that the Queen gave out ſhe would come in <hi>July</hi> and accordingly moſt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nobility prepared to be here againſt that time but the Counteſs of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> was here in <hi>June</hi> at the delivery, becauſe ſhe was one of the principal Perſons concerned in the Intrigue; and therefore had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Intelligence of the time than the reſt.</p>
            <p>Another thing which diverted the thoughts of thoſe who were obſervant and watchfull enough to enquire into all the proceedings of this affair, was the unexpected Impriſonment of the Biſhops, which put all people into an amazement and conſternation; and prevented the attendance of thoſe Prelates at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35401:7"/> Delivery: Whoſe concern for the Proteſtant Religion, and that Juſtice ſhould be done the Princeſſes of <hi>Orange</hi> and <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> would have put them upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ſuch ſatisfaction in the matter as ſhould not have been conſiſtent with an Impoſture, which could not have been reaſonably denied to Perſons of their Character, and ſeeing their Teſtimony would have fully ſatisfied the Nation, their being ſhut up in the <hi>Tower</hi> at that time gives ſtrong ground of ſuſpicion, that their preſence at the pretended De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery could by no means have been admitted, becauſe then the Intrigue had been diſcovered, and their being Priſoners in the <hi>Tower</hi> was the beſt pretence which could be made uſe of why they ſhould not be preſent.</p>
            <p>But there is yet a much ſtronger ground of ſuſpicion than any of thoſe hitherto mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> That tho we had an Ambaſſador reſiding in <hi>Holland,</hi> yet the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> was not invited till almoſt the 10th of <hi>June,</hi> tho' her Royal Highneſs was the Party who by the Law abovementioned ſhould have had notice of the Queens bigneſs; when ſhe intended
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35401:7"/> to lie in and where, and whom it was their Intereſt to have preſent, for avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all Objections, and the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies which might otherwiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue; but ſo it was, that ſhe had no Invitation till it was impoſſible for her to be here at the time of the Delivery; whereas the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth</hi> was ſent for in <hi>April</hi> and came in <hi>May.</hi> Nor is there any reaſon to be given why the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> ſhould not have been urg'd to be preſent if the pregnancy had been real, ſeeing her preſence might have been had much more eaſily, and would have every whitt been as ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to the people as that of the Princeſs of <hi>Orange;</hi> but ſo far were they from ſuch a Juſt and fair procedure, that it was ſo managed as the two Ladies who ought to have been at the labour, for the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> did not come till the Child was dreſs't.</p>
            <p>Then as to thoſe Proteſtant Ladies who were preſent in the room at the time of the pretended Birth, it was ſo ordered by the Kings Introducing men, that there was a neceſſity of covering the Queen, ſo that the ſaid Ladies could not be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35401:8"/> Witneſſes to every thing that they ought to have ſeen, which gave, the Midwife an opportunity of managing the Cheat as ſhe pleaſed; and thus inſtead of being able to depoſe that they ſaw the Child taken out of the Queens body, they could only ſay that they ſaw it taken out of the Bed, and that ſuch things may be conſiſtent with a Cheat is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Inſtance in <hi>Siderfin</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports <hi>Temp. Car. II;</hi> where we have an account of a Woman who pretended to be delivered in bed by a Midwife, but the Impoſture was diſcovered afterward by the ſaid Midwife, and the true Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Then quickly after the pretended Birth, the Child is ſent to <hi>Richmond,</hi> ſeparate from the Queen, that ſhe might be eas'd of the trouble of a forced fondneſs, which being continually to have been acted muſt needs at laſt have grown ſo Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeous that it would have been Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, whereas if the Child had been really her own her fondneſs would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly never have admitted of ſuch a ſeparation, conſidering that he was her only Child, and one upon whoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35401:8"/> life the reſtitution of the Popiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did ſo much depend.</p>
            <p>The next thing that occurs is the time and manner of taking the depoſitions to prove the reality of this pretended Prince's Birth. The time was after they had been charged with the Impoſture all over <hi>Europe,</hi> and when the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was juſt ready to make his deſcent, whereas if the thing had been fair they had it in their Choice to have avoided that trouble by having impartial Eye Witneſſes preſent <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as either or both of the Princeſſes or their deputies, whoſe Teſtimony would have ſatisfied the World.</p>
            <p>Then as to the manner whereas Law and Reaſon require that when any thing is controverted the Opponent ought alſo to have Liberty to bring Witneſſes, and to put Croſs Interrogatories to the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants Evidence, here was no ſuch thing practicable, moſt of the Witneſſes were of the party tho of different Religions, many of them had their dependance on
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35401:9"/> the Court and none of them durſt ſwear any thing contrary to their humour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a manifeſt hazard of Life and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, eſpecially when the K. was preſent to overawe them.</p>
            <p>Then as to the Depoſitions themſelves they are all of 'em ſuch as may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with a ſham except that of the Midwife, who being a bigotted Papiſt and a tool fitted to the purpoſe, her depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will neither hold good in Law nor Equity. But to come to particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. D.</hi> was the firſt who gave her at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation but had no Oath adminiſtred to her, and all that ſhe ſaid was, that ſhe was ſent for to the Queens labour and ſtirred not from her till ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> but does not ſay that ſhe was there all the time of the Labour, nor that ſhe ſaw the ſaid Prince really born of the Queens body.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>C—S—hs</hi> Affidavit relates to the Queens Conception, and he tells us of two Reckonings one from the 6th.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35401:9"/> of <hi>September</hi> and the other from the 6th. of <hi>October</hi> following, which was plainly a deſign to correſpond with other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens reckonings, whoſe Children ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to make uſe of, that if one miſs'd the other might hit, and accordingly it happened as appears by Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, for one of them was brought to bed at St. <hi>Albans</hi> in her way from <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and the other was delivered at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, at the very time when the Queen pretended to be in Labour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. T—ni</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> who carried on the Cheat of the Big-belly, ſwears that on the 10th. of <hi>June</hi> in the Morning, the Queen being in Pain bid her ſend for the Midwife, Ladies, and Servants, after which ſhe ſtaid with the Queen till ſhe was delivered of the Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> This deponent does not ſay neither that ſhe ſaw the Prince come from the Queens body, and gives ſtrong preſumptions of a Cheat; it being very ſtrange that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an hour of the pretended Labour the Queen ſhould have the Midwife, Ladies, and Servants all abſent, ſo that it's plain
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35401:10"/> they were ſent from about her on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that there might not be too many Wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes of the Impoſture, and then when all things were prepared, they were ſent for.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>D—n.</hi> Being one of thoſe ſent for from St. <hi>James</hi>'s Chapel, ſwears that when ſhe came ſhe found the Queen all alone, who bid her get ready the Pallet Bed which ſtood in the next room, but it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never been Aired, ſhe diſſwaded the Queen from making uſe of it; ſhe depoſes farther that ſhe ſaw fire carried into the Queens room in a Warming pan to Warm the bed, and that Mrs. <hi>Wilks</hi> Warm'd it. Its plain from this depoſition that the Queen was left alone which is wholly incredible had her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour been real, and therefore muſt have been contrived on purpoſe for the ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Cheat. The ſtory of the Warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-pan which was alſo covered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the truth of the Aſſertion that the Child was brought in the ſame from the true Mother: Nor is it ſuppoſeable, if the Queen had been in ſuch hard Labour
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35401:10"/> as they give out (and as is evident the true Mother had certainly been, ſeeing the Child was ſtunn'd) that ſhe could have been in a Condition to riſe and have her bed Warm'd; and then from Mrs. <hi>Wilks</hi> Warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bed it appears plain enough that the taking the Child out of the pan and putting it into the Bed was her province, which might eaſily be done, the Curtains being drawn and none about the Bed but the Conſpirators. Then as to the Pallet bed. which had been moſt proper for the Queen if the pregnancy had been real, here's a Cunningly contrived excuſe why it ſhould not be made uſe of. And as to the fire in the Warming-pan there's none of the other Deponents who ſwears that they ſaw it, which its probable they would have done had it been to be ſeen, but as we noted before, the pan was covered ſo that ſhe could not well ſee it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S—d</hi> Another of the Deponents ſays that the Queen after ſome Lingring Pains ſaid ſhe feared ſhe ſhould not be brought to bed a great while, and the Midwife anſwered that ſhe only wanted one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35401:11"/> thorough Pain to bring the Child into the world.—to which the Queen anſwered, 'twas impoſſible the Child lies ſo high, and commanded the Deponent to lay her hand on her Belly.—She adds that a great Pain came at paſt nine of the Clock and the Queen was delivered, which ſhe knew becauſe Mrs. <hi>Wilks</hi> pluckt her by the Coat which was the Sign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on that the Queen was delivered and of a Boy. This Dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Queen and the Midwife might be contrived on purpoſe to cover the Impoſture, and the Deponent does not ſay whether ſhe laid her hand upon the Queens naked belly, ſo that we are to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhe laid her hand upon it no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than thro' the Bedcloaths, or if ſhe did ſhe gives us no account what poſture ſhe found it in, and whereas ſhe ſays that a great Pain came at paſt nine a Clock and the Queen was delivered; it muſt be obſerved that after Eight of the Clock the Queen was ſo well that the King and all her Servants left her alone, ſo that after her beginning to feel pain and calling the people <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It was not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35401:11"/> above three Quarters of an hour ere ſhe was brought to bed and yet ſhe Skreems and they talk of Pains as one that had long and hard labour, tho nothing is ſo inconſiſtent with her being delivered abed covered, none aſſiſting or helping, tho' many ſtanding by as in the moſt eaſie Labours, and the Child ſtunn'd as in the hardeſt. Then by the Midwife's plucking the Deponent by the Coat which was a Sign of the Queens being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered of a Boy, it is apparent that the Deponent no nor other ſaw the Child born, but only taken out of the Bed where it was laid, Neither can any Midwife ſee of what Sex the Child is before the Burthen is drawn out, without detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Woman brought to bed, which it's not ſuppoſeable the Queen would hazard to ſatisfie the Midwife's Curioſity and therefore this Item muſt be by a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge. The <hi>C.</hi> of <hi>R</hi>—depoſes no more than that ſhe ſaw the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> when he was taken out of the bed which is conſiſtent enough with a Cheat as hath been ſaid already.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35401:12"/>
            <p>The Depoſitions of the <hi>C.</hi> of <hi>T—, Hen.</hi> Lady <hi>W</hi>—. and Mrs. <hi>A. C—y</hi> are much the ſame.</p>
            <p>The <hi>C.</hi> of <hi>L—d</hi> Depoſes that ſhe was not at the Labour, but was almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly with the Queen while ſhe was with child, hath put on her Smock; ſeen the Milk run out of her Breaſt and felt her Belly, ſo that ſhe is ſure ſhe could not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. It is to be obſerved that this Lady does not ſwear ſhe ſaw the Milk run out of the Queens Nipple, and its eaſie enough by applying a Spunge with milk to the Queens Breaſt to make milk drop thro her Shift in that part: or if ſhe did real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee milk drop from the Breaſt. its known that there are Women who have milk in their Breaſts that have not been pregnant for many years. Then as to the feeling of her Belly, ſhe does not ſay when, or whether it was ſince the Jealouſie of the Cheat became publick, and it appears by her being in Child-bed her ſelf at the very time when the Queen pretended to be ſo, that ſhe could not for a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35401:12"/> time before put on the Queen's Smock as ſhe lay in Bed, without great inconveniency to her ſelf: and the Queen might eaſily Counterfeit ſuch a Bigneſs as was neceſſary to deceive the Deponent, conſidering the time ſhe pretended to be gone with Child. Madam <hi>B—y</hi>'s Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition being of the ſame nature needs no other anſwer. Dame <hi>J—a W—e</hi> depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſhe put the after burden in a Baſon of Water, which being done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Drs. view'd it, gives juſt cauſe of ſuſpicion that it was in order to prevent a diſcovery of its not having the natural warmth it ſhould have had, if the Drs. had been minded to examine it.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>D—dy</hi> Swears that Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> the Midwife told her that immediately on the next pain the Queen would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered which accordingly ſhe was, but ſays nothing of her having ſeen her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</p>
            <p>The Mar. of <hi>P—s</hi> Swears in the ſame manner as to the milk, and that ſhe ſaw the Child taken out of the Bed; which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35401:13"/> as has been ſaid already is conſiſtent enough with a Cheat.</p>
            <p>The Lady <hi>B</hi>—depoſes that when ſhe came, ſhe found Mrs. <hi>Wilks</hi> ſitting by the Bed-ſide with her hands in the Bed, which is the principal Evidence of a great many, and was certainly done to keep the Child from ſmoothering. She depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alſo as to the Midwives ſaying that the next great pain the Child would be born, whereupon the King called the Privy Counſellors in, and immediately the Queen ſhreeks, and the Prince was born: ſo that here's ſtill nothing but what may be conſiſtent with a Cheat, for neither ſhe nor any of the Privy Counſellors ſaw him born, nor had they the liberty of look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that place where the Child lay hid. Nor were there any of the Drs. that came time enough to be at the Labour.</p>
            <p>It is alſo to be obſerved that there's a Contradiction betwixt the Evidence of Mrs. <hi>W—s,</hi> and that of this Deponent Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> would intimate that aſſoon as ſhe cut the Navel ſtring the Child cried:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35401:13"/> The Navel ſtring was cut in bed, and therefore it muſt by this reaſon cry in bed. But this Deponent <hi>B.</hi> ſays that ſhe opened the Receiver (ſo that the Child was out of Bed) and not hearing the Child cry and ſeeing it lie black, ſhe was afraid it was in a Convulſion fit.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>C—e</hi> depoſes that ſhe ſaw all that was to be ſeen after the Birth of a Child, that is an After-burthen and bloody Clouts, which were no doubt all of 'em conveyed into the Bed as the Child was, for ſhe does not Swear that ſhe ſaw the After-burthen taken from the Queen's Body.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>M—on,</hi> Says he found the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> waiting at the Queen's Bedchamber-door which was then ſhut; and that juſt after the King opened it, and called the Deponent and the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> in. The Deponent askt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty how the Queen was, who anſwered the Deponent, you are a Married-man and may know theſe matters, the Water is broke, or come away. Its obſervable
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35401:14"/> that there was no body in the Room when this is ſaid to be, but Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> ſo that it depends wholly between the Queen, Mrs. <hi>W's</hi> and the King's ſaying ſo. He adds that all the Company were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into the Queen's Chamber, where he heard the Queen Groan, and preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeveral loud Shreeks; and heard them ſay the Queen was delivered. This is all nothing but hear-ſay; he does not ſwear that he ſaw any thing: And as for the Shreeks and Groans it follows naturally, that ſeeing they counterfeited a Birth, they muſt alſo counterfeit the Pains. All that he ſays further to the point is that he ſaw the Midwife put her Hands and Arms in the Bed and fetch out a Child, whence it is evident that he did not ſee the Child born.</p>
            <p>The E. of <hi>H—n</hi> ſays nothing materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, but that the King ſaid the Queen came according to her firſt reckoning; and yet we find ſhe was very ill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for it.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:35401:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>S—er</hi> depoſes no more but that ſhe was at ſuch a Labour, and went with the Child into the little Bed-chamber and took a warm Napkin and laid on its Breaſt, believing the Child was not well; which was the very conſequent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of not cutting the Navel.</p>
            <p>The E—s of <hi>M—fort</hi> and <hi>M—y</hi> Swear only that they heard the Ladies ſay the Queen was brought to Bed, and that they verily believed it was the Queen's Child, which is ſo ſuperficial that there's no need of any Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>La—y, So—a, Bu—y,</hi> ſay ſhe came not till after Nine, and being told the Child was born run to the Queen's Bedſide, and heard the Queen ſay to the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, pray Mrs. <hi>W—s,</hi> don't part the Child, which is nothing at all material.</p>
            <p>The next thing to be conſidered is the not cutting the Navel ſtring, which kept the Child from crying in the Bed or Warming-pan; for the Navel-ſtring by a natural ordination of Nature keeps the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35401:15"/> Child from opening the mouth, nor ſo long as the Navel-ſtring is uncut has the Child any occaſion of the mouth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that he receives nouriſhment by that as we do by the Mouth, and till he was deprived of that he could not do any office that the mouth is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to, ſo that notwithſtanding it is an impracticable thing not to cut the Navel ſtring, yet they paſſed over that as being indeed obliged to do it to keep the Child quiet, and by this means alſo they ſhewed the afterburden in a more identified manner of a late Birth (which they were obliged to) than had the Burden been parted and not left fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened to the Child, for had they cut it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Blood would either have run out, or retired and made that part from whence it went cold, and much unlike the other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Le—x,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Ma—l,</hi> Dame <hi>Iſ. Wo—ch.</hi> and Lady <hi>P—w</hi> do all of them Depoſe that they ſaw milk of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on her Majeſties Smock, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which has been anſwered already—And the latter Swears that ſhe felt the Child ſtir
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35401:15"/> in the Queens Belly; but does not tell us whether ſhe did really feel the Queens na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Belly or only thro the Cloths.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>P—ſe</hi> Swears ſhe heard the Q. Cry out, ſaw the afterburden and by the waſhing of the Linen knew the Q. was in the ſame Condition that other Women uſe to be in on the like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; which as has been ſaid already might all of them eaſily be counterfeited, and there's no doubt but the Linen made uſe of by the real Mother might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to come from the Queen.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>G—n</hi> depoſes that he was called into the Bed Chamber and ſtood near the Chimney where he heard the Queen Cry. Coll. <hi>G—n</hi> depoſes that the King called them into the Bed Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber after that he and ſeveral Lords of the Council had waited about half an hour, whence it appears that they dar'd not to approach till the King called. And Immediately after the Queen cried out Extreamly and ſaid, Oh I die, I die, you kill me, you kill me, then preſently Mrs.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35401:16"/> 
               <hi>D—n</hi> made this Deponent the ſign that the Child was born. The Lord <hi>F—m</hi> waited on the Queen <hi>Dowager</hi> to Saint <hi>James</hi>'s and led her into the Q. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort's Bed Chamber then went into the next room and heard the Queen Crie out ſeveral times, and afterwards ſaw the Prince as a Child newly born. Sir <hi>St. F—x</hi>'s the Earl of <hi>M—ves</hi>'s E. of <hi>Pet—h</hi>'s <hi>A—l</hi>'s E. <hi>Su—d</hi>'s and Lord <hi>Geff—y</hi>'s depoſitions all of 'em lay the ſtreſs on hearing the Queen crie out and ſeeing the Child foul, and as the latter ſays reeking, all which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent enough with a Cheat, for the Child might be brought in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from the true Mother's Apartments and yet appear as they have depoſed, Dr. <hi>W—ly</hi> depoſes he was preſent when the Prince was born, but does not ſay he ſaw him born, he ſays likewiſe he ſaw him foul and the after-burthen, and that he and other Phyſicians took two drops of blood from the Navel ſtring and gave it the Child in a ſpoonfull of <hi>Black-Cherry</hi> water by the Queens Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Dr. <hi>Sc—h</hi> ſays he found the Q.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35401:16"/> in good Condition, but weary and pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (which it was eaſie for her to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit.) And that the above ſaid Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine of giving the Child ſome drops of Blood from its own Navel-ſtring being mentioned among the Ladies, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted Sir <hi>T. W—ly</hi> and the other Phyſicians, who allowed it as conceiving it no way dangerous, which proves the falſehood of Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> and <hi>D—e's</hi> Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who ſaid that it was adminiſtred at the deſire and advice of the Phyſicians.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>W. W—ve</hi> depoſes that her Majeſty took aſtringent Medicines du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of her being with Child to prevent miſcarriage, but does not ſwear that he ſaw her take them. The like is to be ſaid as to Mr. <hi>St—lt—d</hi>'s preparing Reſtringent Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for the Queen; ſeeing he does not Swear that he ſaw her take them.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>B—ys</hi> Depoſition is only that he ſaw the Child in Mrs. <hi>Labady</hi>'s lap, and the Navel-ſtring hanging down towards the Virile parts, which is nothing at all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35401:17"/> to the purpoſe: And now having gone thro all the Depoſitions, I ſhall conclude with this Obſervation upon the whole, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe that gave them in were for the moſt part partial, unfit or illegal perſons; and their Examination manag'd with apparent deſign and partiality, ſo that if they had been really more poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and particular than they are, it could not have been ſuſtained as Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Evidence.</p>
            <p>Then if all this be compared with Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Diſcovery, the Impoſture can no longer remain a doubt.</p>
            <p>The Subſtance of his Diſcovery is thus, That in <hi>May</hi> 1688, the Counteſs of <hi>Tyrconel,</hi> brought over with her from <hi>Ireland</hi> in the <hi>Monmouth</hi> Yacht, Captain <hi>Wright</hi> Commander, two Gentlewomen bigg with Child, the firſt was brought to Bed at St. <hi>Albans</hi> in her way to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but the 2d whoſe name was Mrs. <hi>Gray,</hi> was conveyed to the Pallace of St. <hi>James</hi>'s, and Lodg'd in two private Rooms over or within the Lady <hi>Strick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35401:17"/> Lodgings in the narrow Gallery, between the Queen's Apartment and the Great Chapel: In theſe Lodgings this Mrs. <hi>Gray</hi> was delivered on <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> the ſame day and but a little time before the Queen pretended to be delivered. About the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of <hi>June,</hi> this young Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was removed to the Marchioneſs of <hi>Powis</hi>'s Apartments, in the ſame Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, the Marchioneſs being then Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the pretended Prince, and Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> was at the ſame time committed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to her Charge and Care.</p>
            <p>At that very time Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> being Page to the Marchioneſs, he did by her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand attend Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> conſtantly, and ſupplyed her with all neceſſaries; ſhe was very little viſited by any but the Marchioneſs, and ſome of her Women on proper occaſions; ſhe very ſeldom deſired to ſtir over the threſhold of her own Lodgings, except ſometimes to viſit the pretended Prince, which ſhe did with a particular Zeal and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> conſtantly attending
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35401:18"/> her thither and back again he obſerved that nothing was ſo warmly fond of the Infant as her ſelf, and when as a peculiar favour ſhe was permitted to take him in her Arms, her Kiſſes and Embraces were more than uſually ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Paſſionate.</p>
            <p>About the middle of <hi>July</hi> following when her ſtrength was improved, it was thought fit by ſome authority from Court ſhe ſhould be tranſported into <hi>France,</hi> and accordingly Mr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> one Father <hi>Sabran</hi> and one Mrs. <hi>Jones</hi> atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to <hi>Dover;</hi> ſhe expreſt a great deal of trouble before ſhe went, and the like on her way, as being compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to viſit <hi>France</hi> againſt her Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and when ſhe took her farewel of the pretended young Prince ſhe betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an extraordinary Concern, and burſt forth into Tears. She was met at <hi>Dover</hi> by one Father <hi>Grey</hi> a Prieſt, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be her Brother and Embarkt for <hi>Calis,</hi> in order to be conveyed to the Convent of <hi>Benedictin Nuns</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> ſhe having been in a Nunnery in <hi>Ireland</hi> before.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35401:18"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> being after this preferred to the Queen's Service, he went over to <hi>France</hi> with her Majeſty and the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Prince at the Revolution; and the Queen putting great truſt in him upon the Marchioneſs of <hi>Powis</hi>'s Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, in <hi>February</hi> 1689, her Majeſty ſent for him to St. <hi>Germains</hi> one <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> night to her Chamber, where ſhe kept being as 'twas reported indiſpoſed, by ſome Fright, her Majeſty told him that he muſt prepare immediately to go for <hi>England</hi> with Letters to the Lord <hi>Montgomery</hi> and others about extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary buſineſs. She did accordingly give him her Letters, telling him that it was a matter that nearly concern'd the K. and her ſelf, and if he ſhould happen by a ſtrict ſearch to be obliged to throw his Letters into the Sea or otherwiſe ſhe gave him a Ring, which he was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver to the Lord <hi>Montgomery,</hi> by way of Credentials for what he had to ſay to him by word of Mouth, which was to tell him that the ſame Woman which came from <hi>Ireland</hi> with the Lady <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connel</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:35401:19"/> in <hi>May</hi> 1688, was ſtolen out of the Nunnery in <hi>Paris,</hi> where ſhe was kept (there having been a breach in the Garden-walls) and that it was the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the French Court that ſhe had been aſſiſted by ſome of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Friends in <hi>Paris,</hi> to make her eſcape from thence, in order to come for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> She Commanded him alſo to tell the Lord <hi>Montgomery</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> King had taken all poſſible care to prevent her going off, but leaſt his Endeavours might prove ineffectual it was her deſire that immediately after Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Arrival in <hi>England</hi> the Ld. <hi>Montgomery</hi> and others ſhould take care to place people on the Coaſt of <hi>England</hi> that might inform them when ſhe Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and then they were poſitively com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to uſe all Endeavours to get her diſpatched to prevent whatever deſigns ſhe might pretend to. Mr. <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> having received his orders ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for <hi>England</hi> and came as far as <hi>Abbeville</hi> where he delivered a Letter to Father <hi>Peters</hi> requiring him to go to St. <hi>Omers</hi> to obſerve whether or no
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35401:19"/> the Woman might come that way in order to her embarquing for <hi>England,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Crane</hi> Gentleman Uſher to the late Q. arriving in the mean time with a Counter order commanding him to return to St. <hi>Germans,</hi> the Q. told him that the loſt ſheep was found at a private houſe in <hi>Paris,</hi> and was now under the care of the Counteſs of <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> and Father <hi>Sabran</hi> went in one of the Queens Coaches to bring the Counteſs and Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> to St. <hi>Germains,</hi> where the latter was conveyed privately to the Queen by Mr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> and ſhe ſtaid in her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Chamber, together with the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs of <hi>Powis,</hi> the Counteſs of <hi>Suſſex</hi> and others above an hour, and was afterwards conveyed to a private Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment belonging to the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> where ſhe continued a day or two, after which the late Queen and the whole Court went to viſit the <hi>French</hi> King at <hi>Marli</hi> three miles from St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> and that ſame Evening Mr. <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> Father <hi>Sabran,</hi> the Counteſs of <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:35401:20"/> and Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> went thither in the Prince's Coach with ſix Horſes and were conveyed to a room belonging to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> while the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs went publickly to wait upon the <hi>French</hi> King and the late Queen; after which Mr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> Father <hi>Sabran,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> were conducted privately to the <hi>French</hi> King's Backſtairs, the poor Woman Lamenting her hard fate mean while, which ſhe ſaid was occaſioned by her laſt being in <hi>England,</hi> ſhe grieved ſo exceſſively that ſhe fainted ſeveral times before they could get her to the <hi>French</hi> Kings apartment, whither ſhe was conducted by a Jeſuit, and where ſhe continued about half an hour with the <hi>French</hi> King and the late Queen: being brought down again by that ſame Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, ſhe wept bitterly and told Father <hi>Sabran</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> that now ſhe muſt take her everlaſting farewell of them, and ſo ſhe was carried away by the ſaid Jeſuit, and never more ſeen nor heard of by Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> tho' he made moſt diligent Enquiry after her at all the <hi>Engliſh, Scots</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Nunneries</hi> in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35401:20"/> 
               <hi>Paris</hi> and other places where he had great acquaintance, and Father <hi>Sabran</hi> who was Chaplain to the pretended Prince and is now his Tutor, did frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> that he believed ſhe would not be alive the day following, nor was it fit ſhe ſhould live.</p>
            <p>He adds that beſides his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in this affair there have been ſeveral Letters and Papers found in Mrs. <hi>Labadie</hi>'s Fathers Trunk relating to Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> and the whole Intrigue, beſides ſeveral Corroborating proofs from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perſons of quality in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and others; as alſo the Captain that brought her over from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and him that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her over to <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to his not publiſhing his Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſooner, he anſwers, that it was laid before the King and Queen in 1690. that many others have been examined in this matter, whoſe depoſitions agree with his, and that the Lord <hi>Preſton</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Crone</hi>'s Confeſſions upon Oath cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborate his, but that the Lord <hi>N</hi>—
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35401:21"/> would not ſuffer him to Print his own defence, and did alſo prevent the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Madam <hi>Labadies</hi> Letters, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Queens Command, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending they were miſllaid.</p>
            <p>To Conclude then, it's evident that all theſe things being laid together they amount to as full and Concluding a demonſtration of the Impoſture of the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> as the thing is capable of, except the parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned ſhould actually confeſs it. The bringing of this Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> bigg with Child from <hi>Ireland</hi> and her being brought to bed in St. <hi>James</hi>'s at the very time when the Queen pretended to be brought to be confirms all the Exceptions made againſt the Evidence in the foregoing ſheets, and ſeeing there's none of the depoſitions but what may conſiſt with a Cheat except Mr. <hi>Wilks</hi>'s who was a tool fitted to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it is the ſtrongeſt Confirmation Imaginable that all the ſteps of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture here related are certainly true.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:35401:21"/>
            <p>But the Impoſture appears ſtill in more lively Colours when we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the former part of this Hiſtory with Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Narrative, for it Mrs. <hi>Grey</hi> was not the Mother of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Prince, why ſhould ſhe above all others have the Privilege of hug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him, why ſhould ſhe have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered ſo much concern at leaving him, why ſhould the late Queen be in ſuch a Mortal fright at her eſcaping out of the <hi>Nunnery</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> why ſhould ſhe Imagine that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s friends contributed to that Eſcape, why ſhould ſuch bloody and poſitive orders have been given for her deſtruction, and ſuch care taken to prevent her ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival in <hi>England</hi> or at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and why when found again, ſhould the <hi>French</hi> King have been ſo much concerned in the matter as to Examine her, and why ſhould ſuch bloody Expreſſions have dropt from Father <hi>Sabran's</hi> mouth as that he believed ſhe would not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live next day, and that it was not fit ſhe ſhould live, if they were not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to themſelves that ſhe was the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35401:22"/> true Mother and that therefore it was their Intereſt to prevent any poſſibility of her making a diſcovery, the fear of which had put them into ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and the Conſequences of which might have been ſo dangerous to them ſo that upon the whole there's no man who is not poſſeſs't with invincible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice but muſt needs be convinced of the impoſture deſigned to be put upon the Nation in this affair.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:35401:22"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
            <p>THe Character of <hi>Charles</hi> II. King of <hi>England.</hi> With a ſhort account of his being Poyſoned. Written by a Perſon of Honour. With an Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction exhibiting the Different Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters given him by the ſeveral dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Parties of Roman Catholicks, Churchmen, and Diſſenters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother hand. <hi>London</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms-Inn</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> 1696. Price <hi>6d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings, taught <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and <hi>James</hi> II. By the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites. Wherein is Diſcovered, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of the laſt Conſpiracy, form'd at <hi>Verſailles</hi> in <hi>Sep.</hi> 1695. againſt the Life of <hi>William</hi> III. King of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> And diſcovered at <hi>White-Hall, Feb.</hi> 1691. Done out of <hi>French.</hi> Price <hi>1s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The State of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia:</hi> Or a Dialogue betwixt <hi>Jack.</hi> and <hi>Will.</hi> concerning the Times. Both ſold by <hi>E. Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35401:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35401:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35401:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35401:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
